A Guide to the Jacob W. Lantz Papers, 1908-1944
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Jacob W. Lantz Papers, 1908-1944
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1975-003
1.5 cu. ft. 3 boxes
Correspondence and account books of Jacob W. Lantz, proprietor of a general store in Smythe County, Virginia, and manager of local properties owned by the Lobdell Car Wheel Company.
Lantz, Jacob W., 1868-1940
Adminstrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Jacob W. Lantz Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1975.
Biographical Note
Jacob Wissler Lantz, son of Jacob and Elizabeth Lantz, was born October 21, 1868, at Lantz's Mills (Shenandoah County), Virginia. In his early years, Lantz moved to Max Meadows (Wythe County), Virginia and entered business with his uncle, Jacob H. Wissler. On April 8, 1896, Lantz married Clara Virginia Keesling, daughter of Emory S. and Emmaline (Derting) Keesling, of Cedar Springs (Smyth County), Virginia.
Lantz served in various capacities managing the local properties of the Lobdell Car Wheel Company until 1895, when he established the Cedar Springs Company, a general mercantile store. He also owned a flour mill in nearby Grayson County, engaged in the real estate and private banking businesses, and served as a director of the First National Bank of Rural Retreat, Virginia. Lantz apparently resumed managing the Lobdell properties in the 1930s.
A member of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, Lantz served for several years as president of the Virginia Sunday School Association. He also had a longstanding interest in the history of the Lantz family and in 1931 self-published The Lantz Family Record. Jacob Lantz died on March 16, 1940.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains papers of Jacob W. Lantz, proprietor of a general store in Cedar Springs (Smyth County), Virginia. The collection contains correspondence, financial documents, and account books.
The correspondence relates largely to Lantz's business affairs, particularly the management of his store and the local properties of the Lobdell Car Wheel Company. Together with correspondence between Lantz and various suppliers, the general store folder includes receipts and promotional material. The Lobdell Car Wheel Company file consists mostly of correspondence between Lantz and company secretary Howard L. Seaman but also includes correspondence with others, all relating to local property management issues. A folder devoted to Lantz's personal financial interests includes (among other things) letters from various relatives seeking loans. Among the correspondence also are personal letters, several relating to Lantz's church activities. A separate folder contains correspondence and notes relating to Lantz's interest in his family's history.
Most of the account books in the collection are unidentified. Among the volumes is an account book apparently kept by a shoe cobbler during the early 20th century. Other ledgers in the collection seem to detail the income and expenditures of mercantile and produce businesses. Also included are a set of ledgers providing a detailed general store inventory from 1938 to 1942.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Lobdell Car Wheel Company Account Books, 1881-1902. Ms1940-019.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Geographical Names:
Smyth County (Va.)
Contents List
- Personal correspondence, 1935-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Lantz genealogy, 1926-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Personal financial, 1934-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Cedar Springs Company, 1934-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Lobdell Car Wheel Company, 1930-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5-7)
- Double-entry ledger, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Cobbler accounts book, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Monthly account balances journals, 1935-1941 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Sales books (Box-folder 2-1-6)
  - 1938
  - 1941
  - Jan-Jun 1943
  - Jul-Dec 1943
  - Jan-Jun 1944
  - Jul-Dec 1944
- Cash book, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 2-7)
- Produce sales and expenditures, [1940]-1943 (Box-folder 3-1)
- Store inventories, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 3-2-6)